Preliminary Guide to the Walter Johnson Robb Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Walter Johnson Robb papers
1919-1969
1940-1946
MS 740
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, clippings, photographs, financial papers and memorabilia documenting Robb's career in the Philippines as a correspondent and, during World War II, as a lecturer for the Office of War Information (O.W.I.). The writings include manuscripts of articles by Robb on the Philippines, texts of his broadcasts for the O.W.I., and poetry. Among his correspondents are Henry Andreas, Raymond L. Buell, Percy Hill, Sergio Osmeña, Chick Parsons, and Will Rogers, Jr.
Robb, Walter Johnson, 1880-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter Robb, 1969.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This unprocessed collection of Walter Johnson Robb Papers pertains primarily to the Philippine Islands. It includes personal correspondence with Henry Andreas, Raymond L. Buell, Percy Hill, Sergio Osmeña, Chick Parsons, and Will Rogers, Jr., as well as other residents of the Philippines and family members, and business correspondence with publishers, editors of newspapers and journals, government offices, and other organizations. Mixed in with the correspondence are financial papers such as bank statements, cancelled checks, receipts, brokers' reports, deeds of sale, and promissory notes.
Also in the collection are newspaper clippings by Robb and others about the Philippines, Viet Nam and Asia; typescripts and manuscripts of articles by Robb about the Philippines, as well as some printed matter by others; poetry by Robb; and the texts of Robb's radio broadcasts to the Philippines during 1945-1946. There are, in addition, miscellaneous business papers, notes and printed matter concerning A.T. & T. and other topics, items such as calling cards, invitations and so forth, and a selection of photographs, mostly of people and places in the Philippines.
These papers were the gift of Walter Johnson Robb to Yale University in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Walter J. Robb: author; educated in schools in Kansas and Oklahoma; teacher, country schools in Oklahoma, 1896-1907; teacher, Philippine civil service, 1907-1918; newspaper work and foreign news correspondent, Manila, 1918-1941; public lecturer on war in Pacific, 1942-1943; assistant field correspondent, Foreign Broadcast Intelligence Service, San Francisco, 1943-1944; writer, O.W.I., overseas branch, San Francisco, Philippine Division, 1945-1946.
Americans -- Philippines; Journalism; World War, 1939-1945 -- Philippines; Asia; Philippines -- Description and travel; Journalists; Andreas, Henry; Buell, Raymond Leslie, 1896-1946; Hill, Percy A., -1937; Osmeña, Sergio, 1878-1961; Parsons, Charles A.; Robb, Walter Johnson, 1880-; Rogers, Will, 1912-2008; United States. Office of War Information
- Inventory
  - Correspondence and financial papers, 1923-1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and financial papers, 1948-1969, undated (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings and other printed matter
    - Re: the Philippines, 1903-1946 (Box 2)
    - Re: Viet Nam, 1965-1968 (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts, 1930-1941, undated (Box 3)
  - Poetry and other writings, 1936-1941, undated (Box 3)
  - Papers re: A.T. & T., 1951 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous business papers, notes, printed matter, etc., 1919-1946, undated (Box 3)
  - Radio broadcasts, 1945-1946 (Box 4)
  - Photographs and drawings, 1916, [ca. 1940-1946] (Box 4)
  - Synopsis of Lectures, Office of War Information. Far East Training Course, 1944 (Box 4)